welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us through thank
you john great to be here
so greg i wanted to follow up on some of
the points we had gotten to
last time we've been talking a lot about
you know aspectualization and things
like that
and disrespectful knowing and what i
thought we'd do is do a case study that
will help to make these ideas
uh more concrete and understandable but
it will also give me more information by
which i can advance the argument and
make proposals
about the nature of consciousness amen
that sounds good
yep okay so i'm gonna do something i
don't normally like to do especially
when we're in dialogue like this
uh but i am gonna sort of
share my screen and because i got some
slides um
because i'm riffing off of the talk i've
given in two separate occasions
keep modifying it of course and i want
to sort of run this with you and run
through it
uh with you so well since i often share
slides john then it would be
uh this is you know this is a good thing
this balances us out
okay so that's fine for you okay so what
i want to talk about is
oh i want to start with an
acknowledgement uh right from the
beginning
um why it's called seeing into being on
mars and beyond it's about how
nasa scientists on earth use the rovers
on mars in order to do field work yeah
right um and it's going to turn out that
this is a very powerful case study
that will help us to tell uh get a lot
of more understanding about perspectival
knowing
and then another kind of knowing that i
think we've alluded to a couple times
participatory knowing
and then bring that into uh more
directly into the discussion of
consciousness
i do want to begin with an
acknowledgement that a lot of this work
is has been done and continues to be
done with another good friend of mine
dan shappy who's at the
university of california long beach and
so we are doing this ongoing work
so i know i don't i i owe a lot to dan
in this argument i'm not going to keep
referencing him so i want to give a
global thing
right right up front right from the
beginning great
all right so the rovers on mars are a
really exemplary study
of a lot of the four e themes that we've
been talking about
embodiment embedded enacted extended
um and the main problem i want to
address
at least initially in what we're going
through here
has to do with how the scientists using
only very limited
visual information nevertheless get
something that's
crucial to the phenomenology of
consciousness
they get a sense of presence they get a
sense of being
on mars not just looking at pictures
that refer to mars
but the sense of being on mars and
that's important because we've already
been talking about that we've been
talking about this
demonstrative indexicality of
consciousness the sense of
you know that sense of here and now
togetherness this right
is here now togetherness that sense of
presence
and this gives us a really wonderful
case study for investigating that sense
of presence trying to tease it out more
and learn more about consciousness in
the process that's part of what i want
to do here
and so i'm going to go through something
um
which is a little bit along the way i
want to show how the
the generation of theory you know
propositional knowing depends on
procedural abilities with the skills of
what are called field work
yep that in turn depends on situational
awareness which is the primary thing
that is generated by perspective
annoying and then i want to show
how that is ultimately dependent on
something deeper so um
seeing as if you're on mars depending
depends on seeing as if you're the rover
there's a process of identification that
takes place between the scientists
and the rover that is actually necessary
it's a presence and that's going to help
me articulate a bit more about what this
participatory knowing is
now why is that relevant it's relevant
right off the bat
because consciousness has this weird
feature about it
that you know it in you don't only you
not only know consciousness
perspectively
what it's like to be here now you're now
togetherness right we've talked about
that the adverbial qualia
right you know you're conscious by being
conscious you know you're conscious
by being conscious this is the core of
participatory knowing it's knowing by
being
and what's interesting about these
scientists is that they
take on the role of in in obviously not
in a literal sense but in a very
symbolic and active sense
they take on the role of being the rover
and that actually affords them
um the necessary situational awareness
so i want to try and
go through with this one step at a time
okay so let's be clear about a couple
things right from the beginning the
rover send back
batch pictures um you know and they're
in black and white
there is no joystick control there is no
joystick control
uh because of the time delay between
earth and mars
no joystick control what happens is a
buck you know you get batches of
pictures
and then you send in a whole bunch of
commands and then it's a batch of
commands is sent back out
and so and there's terrific time delay
so there's huge displacements in time
and space and type of environment
between the scientists
and the rover okay right
yeah it's the scientists on earth right
who are using the visual information
from the rover to correct you know to
direct and correct the rover
what i mean by that is don't think that
the rover obviously has some ai
but don't think that the rover's ai is
sufficient enough that it's sort of
moving itself around
and doing any work in an autonomous
fashion that's not the case
the scientists are the ones doing the
science through the rover
on mars okay so this is a clear case of
examining what's called extended
cognition
extended cognition is the idea that a
lot of our cognition doesn't take place
in our head
it takes place uh through machines
through tools
through other people through
discrimination it's a clear case of
extended cognition
however so while it picks up on that
theme of extended cognition it seems to
deeply challenge
um the other e's i mean the scientists
are not embodied
right the body the rover body is on mars
they're not embedded on mars and they're
obviously not enacting on mars they're
on earth
typing code into a computer
okay so there's all those problems now
given that most of the e's are missing
the embodiment and the embeddedness
right and the enacted aspects
one might suspect that people have a
very distant displaced
alienated experience uh of of mars
through this medium but that's not
actually the case
and this is the intriguing thing what is
the case
is that
scientists regularly and reliably report
that they feel like they're on mars they
sense being
on mars the way you right now sense that
you're in that room you're in
and i sense that i'm in the room i mean
they have that sense of presence that
we've been talking about
which is really weird if you think about
it
they know what it's like to be a rover
so it's very very odd uh so they
and they report that they're seeing as
the rover they're seeing as if they're
the rover
so john and just in terms of so they are
um
they get these batch photos right um and
obviously these are scientists that are
very familiar
with the machinery of the rover right in
terms of or
or not i guess that's a question that i
would have in relation to varying
degrees
to varying degrees so they they
basically have sort of this
this dynamically restructuring small
world network way in which they organize
themselves and they have various degrees
of expertise and there are people who
are more specialized in sort of
managing and moving the rover and then
there's people who are more like
more like geologists and then there's
people who are
more like meteorologists things like
that so
um in a collective sense yes there's
definitely a gotcha
now what they what what's interesting is
uh
the scientists who are in the group
because they often have to hire new
people
etc there's attrition new problems come
up etc
they report that they look for people
who can
ex who can have that experience who can
sense
have that sense of presence a sense of
being on mars
because the scientists report that that
ability to generate that experience
is actually predictive of the people who
are able to do
good work with the rover okay do good
work
do good field work on mars so it's not
just some sort of weird thing that sort
of jangles over there
it's actually a highly prized experience
that is predictive according to the
scientists at least
of good work okay all right
okay so given how disrupted the 4e
features are how is it the scientists
can never
the less acquire the phenomenological
markers of embeddedness in action
and even as we'll see later embodiment
how do they do that
and and of course all along why are we
doing this
because we're trying to understand this
sense of presence and we're trying to
understand that because
it has a lot to do uh with the
perspectival knowing
that is at the core of consciousness
okay so far yep totally right
okay so we what's fortunate about this
and dan and i
uh you know we're lucky because we live
in the the
age of virtual reality uh video games
etc
and so there's quite a bit of um
there's quite a bit of research on sense
of
presence in video games what are the
features of a video game
that make people have that sense of
being in the game
and when they're correspondingly and
this is important that it's more real to
them
there's there's a deep connection
between sense of presence
and sense of realness and uh
this because and the reason why the
people are doing this research is this
is a highly sought after
feature of uh for example of a video
game so we have two video games
and this one reliably generates sense of
presence
and this one doesn't this one will be
preferred and we'll have much greater
chance of markets inside
over there so there's something
normative there's something inherently
valued probably an evolutionary marker
of some kind
sense of presence seems to be something
organisms
seek out um in about in an important way
we'll try and cover that off
now why is that important well if we can
figure out
how sense of presence is adaptive and
sense of presence
is a way of unders is a case where we
can
you know get into the guts of
perspectival knowing
and a perspectival knowing is central to
consciousness this will give us a
powerful way of
getting it some of the functionality of
consciousness is
consciousness involves perspectival
knowing which generates sense of
presence and we know what the
functionality of sense of presence is
we can start to answer the function
question and of course what's
interesting about sense of presence
is it's not just a functional thing it's
deeply phenomenological
it has a lot to do with the feel of
being conscious
and so we're getting what we've talked
about doing we're getting a case study
right where we can deeply look at the
function question
and the nature question together
okay okay now i'm not going to try and
give
an exhaustive definition of sense of
presence but
that's the whole thing but there's a
couple of key points that need to
um be made clear
as i said the sense of presence is the
sense of being there
uh that indexical sense of here now-ness
and togetherness
things with the adverbial qualia so it's
the but the sense of presence is that
the adverbial qualia
are happening just i mean that's a clear
and easy way of putting it um
so as i mentioned it has a lot to do
with the sense of realness and that it's
normative
and it's valuable
okay now so given the vr
research virtual reality research right
what are the
things that tend to generate this sense
of presence
and why does it have this normative
value for us why is it functional for us
why do we value it why do we seek it out
why do we have
even aesthetic approval for it
okay so a powerful intuition people have
is that what creates sense of presence
is very similitude how realistic
and this is because the sense of
realness you can understand the
intuition
like how realistic the game is is what
actually is conducive
uh to a sense of presence it turns out
that's not the case
it turns out that you can have you know
video games that are quite
realistic and you don't get a sense of
presence and you can have video
other video games like tetris that
generate a tremendous sense of presence
even i was a tetris addict
right did you did you dream in tetris
yeah i mean when i was into it you know
i i pushed the limit on that thing i
was i was definitely into that game i i
was the boxes john
i was boxes well there you go
so the interesting thing about it then
is that
uh you get pretty like on both
you know so i could show it's uh it's
not sufficient
neither is it necessary and so what i'm
not saying that very similitude can't
contribute
what i've given you though is an
argument that it can't be essential
actually this is really interesting
because i did i felt
the shapes of the blocks you know i can
say i didn't i'm really not
not really i can easily access that i
felt the shapes of the blocks and the
structure
i felt the speed i felt the flow right
um
huh that's interesting yeah good yeah
well thank you that
that that further corroborating evidence
which is
helpful and wonderful okay so
one of the interesting ideas is then to
try and so what we've done is we've
problematized this
right and so it's not very similar to
well what is it
so one of my uh uh former students uh
gary
over hennison um in 2019 argued
um that what what is predictive
of the sense of presence is to get into
the flow state
so if you're in the flow state that's
right
that's what predicts a sense of presence
and this is of course very plausible
because when people are in the flow
state they they
state that they're at one with the
environment the environment is super
salient there's an ongoing sense of
discovery
right so it's a very plausible
hypothesis because it's very plausible
for example
that you could have a realistic game
that doesn't get you into the flow state
and therefore you don't get a sense of
presence but you could be in tetris and
get into the flow state
etc okay so this this is i think i think
this is a very plausible account
uh for video games
however the problem is flow's not going
to be the answer for the situation we're
studying
because what you need for flow according
to chicks at my high and all the
replicated work
you know what i need for flow is three
conditions error has to matter
well moving the rovers around error
matters that's so that's definitely
there
right if i screw up that's it the
rover's done to put so that's there but
the two other things i need for
flow is i need clear signal and i need
tightly coupled feedback
but you know what the scientists don't
have they don't have tightly coupled
feedback
because they don't have joystick control
like in a video game
right they don't and they don't get
clear signal they spend
hours arguing over these
deeply ambiguous pictures that come back
from mars
so they don't have clear signal they
don't have
tightly coupled feedback so it looks
like this proposal
that seems to be very plausible for a
getting sense of presence in video games
is not going to work for the scientists
on mars
right but what i can
what i can uh argue is maybe
flow contains within it a more basic
phenomena
that can be nevertheless the case on
mars
all right so maybe flow contains within
it a more basic phenomenon
so maybe flow is a species of a more
generic
process and that generic process might
be sufficient
for explaining the sense of presence
okay
okay so this is the process uh that is
coming up a lot
in 40 cognitive science the idea of
optimal grip
now clearly what's happening in the flow
state is a state of enhanced optimal
grip
so what's optimal grip this is the idea
and we've talked about this before
yeah right the idea that right
i'm constantly trading off between you
know
features and gestalt between familiar
and unfamiliar between the foreground
and the background
and i'm constantly toggling between all
these trade-off relationships
to get the overall optimal set
of features and properties that will
enable
me to deal with the tasks that are at
hand i'm getting an
optimal grip on the situation now flow
is a species of optimal grip
but there are many instances for example
i think i
have a pretty good optimal grip on your
face right now but i'm not sort of in
in the flow state right so what i want
to propose to you
is the flow state is sort of like where
you've got insights that are creating
new instances of optimal grip
but it's actually the optimal grip that
is generating the sense of presence okay
so so let me just summarize so we have
we can create an
a spectralizing form right
around uh the entity
and system that we're in and we're going
to basically now
pull that a specializing form and then
start to engage
a process with it in a particular way
that generates a dynamic engaging
feedback in a way that allows for say a
flow of
energy or whatever kind of you know kind
of dynamic in a particular
investment path i might say yeah that's
that's
that's well put um yes i think that's
actually very well put so the idea here
is the scientists are able to
nevertheless in this very thin
information channel
use it with some cultivated expertise to
get the ultimate optimal grip
that starts to make mars opens up
affordances of intelligibility
for them from mars um so i think that's
very much in concert with what you just
said is that
a hundred percent yeah absolutely okay
great
all right so i've said you know what
what optimal grip is
i've given some components of it gestalt
and we've talked about this before
already uh when we've been talking about
uh consciousness so uh
let's let's just keep going
and so here's the idea i thought this
was uh because we've talked about
aspectuality and centrality and
temporality before
um and so this is the idea is that
up you're you're you're doing the
optimal grip is
toggling things so things are that are
aspectularized
they are relevant to you they're sent
and they're they are temporally
irrelevant
so you get optimal grip that is giving
you a salience landscaping
moving between aspectuality centrality
and temporality and when that salience
landscape
glues you into right the affordances in
the environment right you
feel a sense of press right you feel a
sense of presence
right okay okay
all right so i want to call this
optimal grip sizing up salience
landscaping
that affords situational awareness
because that's what it is
right that's what situational awareness
is it's the salience landscape that
glues you in
to the affordances in the environment i
want to call that whole thing something
we've already been talking about before
perspectival knowing right that's what
perspectival knowing is
it's knowing what it's like to be here
now through in both senses of the word
my current state of mind okay yep so
again deeply part of that aspect of
consciousness
made famous by nagel knowing what it's
like to be
okay go ahead go ahead no i was just
gonna offer
uh just sort of an angle on this so i've
been researching the evolution of
animal consciousness okay right um and
a really interesting 2017 book i think
it was on the evolution animal conscious
or whatever it was talking about
you know a plane of intersection between
interoceptive awareness like what the
body is telling
extra receptive awareness and pleasure
pain
affectivity you know um so just in
relationship to what is this
uh optimal grip doing bringing in
information in a gestalt
understanding where the body wants to go
finding the affordances and the
potential costs
is a nice intersection i think that then
you know corresponds to potentially sets
the stage for
this field of perspectival knowing i i
think that's exactly right
um i know the book you're talking about
i haven't i can't remember the authors
as well right now so
um we're both getting old i guess um so
okay so my my my the main claim i've now
argued too
is that the sense of presence is a
phenomenological feel
of and of and marker for perspectival
knowing
sense of presence is the
phenomenological feel
of respectable knowing okay
so how do scientists generate this
perspectival knowing how do they
see as if they're the rover and the part
of the argument i'm going to make is
they see as if they're
they're over by uh c right
by by by being the rover uh
in a very important way um
all right so for tessie in her excellent
book seeing like a rover
um talks about this so it's an extended
ethnography
she was an anthropologist she went there
she's kind of there's other
ethnographies that corroborate cohere
with this
there's a work that right so extended
ethnography
and she um she talks about this process
and it's very interesting uh what she
calls drawing
ads so the drawing as so
it's based on um well it's based on
aspectualization because it's based on
wittgenstein's notion of seeing ads
remember your example of you see the
picture as a duck
or you see it as a rabbit right so it's
a spectralization that's exactly what
she's talking about right
so what happens is the scientists get
these pictures
right these photos and what they do is
they mark them up
they put color on them they put lines on
them they put arrows on them
they do all this stuff to manipulate the
salience
so and she calls this drawing as and
she's actually playing on the word
because she means drawing as in the
sense of drawing
but also drawing out right now yeah yeah
right
so that you can see it as and the idea
is you get this black and white picture
you don't know what it is
and you do all this stuff that is
actually not vera similitude
you're putting colors on it and all this
right right you're drawing on it you're
in
in in you know in a sense of precision
you're distorting the picture but you
distort it in the way so that
you can then start it as specializes and
you can see it as you go
oh that's a depression there
right the the the topography go oh
oh i see right and there's a textured
gradient there things have
rolled down that hill they look for that
pop out kind of effect right so that
then by putting that angle on it they
pull various aspects of the salience
landscape
together right exactly so what they're
doing is they're doing this
deliberate salience manipulation
right so they're they're deliberately
doing
salience landscaping right externally
on the pictures in order to aspectulize
that information and then what that does
is that makes it available for problem
solving
okay so they're doing all of this
and when they start to do that
right they start to get a bit of what
we're talking about here
but seeing as if you're being on mars
really depends on
and more than just this drawing so one
half of the answer is
the drawing as and it fits right into
this analysis
beautifully that we've been making
together about consciousness and
respectable knowing
and salience landscaping and
aspectualization
and all of that stuff right great but
there's more to it
okay so i talked about the the drawing
as i not we don't need to go through
every um single slide in detail here
it's up there people want to look at it
first testy so we've got the drawing as
process and then vertex talks about this
other set of practices people the
scientists do
so first of all they anthropomorphize
the rover they don't say the rover needs
to go there they'll say
i need to go there or we need to go
there we need i need to move my arm
which means that one of the rovers tools
right and they'll talk about the rover
falling asleep and waking up and they
don't want it to die
right so they anthropomorphized they do
this
you know symbolic identification process
but
they do more than just anthropomorphize
they also and this is a term i think
coined by vertexi
they technomorphize themselves they
technomorphize themselves
so here's um um the
uh the uh sense of presence talking
about
i call it the second sense of presence
because this is a sense of presence
that's
actually being used by the scientists
rather than just one making us feel
wonderful about
mars okay so that's that's just why the
slide has that title okay so here's the
scientists
and notice what the scientists do this
is technomorphizing so the scientists
that she's trying to figure out right
how to adjust the rover and so she puts
her phone down in front and says
you know this the phone is a rock and
then you know these are my cameras and
she's on
like a wheelchair and she starts to turn
her body and then swivel
and move and this is what she's doing
this is what i need to do
and she's using the i language this is
what i need to do
in order to like get this
needed information from
the rover
so there's this loop that's being
created
there's this right anthropomorphizing
from human to rover
but also technomorphizing from rover to
human
so there's this reciprocal
shaping of identity you're
humanizing the rover but you're also
mechanizing you but if
that's even a verb right uh this the
human beings the scientists
and so what you're doing is you're doing
this reciprocal shaping
of identities
so i just want i want to read this out i
won't i know i'm not usually going to
read from
uh but just because the wording here is
a little bit
careful and there's a couple more things
i'm going to have to read i have to read
them for the exp
explicit reason that i'm quoting i'm
literally quoting the scientists okay
so i know reading is a little bit rude i
apologize i i will keep it to a minimum
here we'll keep it to a minimum
but there's an inactive integration of
knowing oneself
through the rover and and knowing the
rover through oneself
so that one is simultaneously knowing
oneself
knowing the rover and knowing through
the rover all of those things are
happening
at the same time which of course is very
similar
to how you know your body all right you
know yourself by knowing your body you
know yourself
by right as having a body but you also
know yourself through the body you know
the world through the body
so they're doing something that is
structurally analogous to embodiment
right
really powerful way now
this mutual shaping is very analogous to
how evolution
in niche construction mutually shapes an
organism in its environment
or how culture mutually shapes you know
uh its participants in the environment
and why does why
why what does this mutual shaping do
well it generates affordances
um so here's a classic example this is
cop
okay so because of evolution here's an
affordance it's graspable we've talked
about something like that before
right so biologically right because of
niche construction
i can grasp it right because it's
uh my hand has evolved to fit
certain shapes in the environment and
there's niche construction right
culturally it's a tool it's a cut and
you know i've been shaped to be a
drinker and then of course i have my
ongoing situational awareness
that i can actually use it so there's
biological affordances
there are cultural affordances and then
there's my direct awareness
of how i can use those affordances
to get a drink right here right now okay
so i want to call that process
by which agent and environment
are co-shaped agents in arena
so that affordances are generated
between them
i want to call that participatory
knowing it's a knowing by being
it's a knowing by being a particular
kind of agent and
being in a particular kind of arena it's
a knowing
by being it's a knowing by being
right so what we're saying is the agent
the the the agent has a sense of what
kind of
agent it is in the arena that it is
right uh i mean that sounded maybe uh i
was being redundant there to just
emphasize the dynamic relation no i
think that was helpful i think that was
i think that what you just did wasn't it
it might have been syntactically
reductive
redundant but i didn't think i don't
think it was semantically redundant i
think it's important
okay so here's one of these quotes i'm
going to read and again i
because i want to show you the
phenomenology i want to make it clear to
people that i'm not attributing things
to the scientists okay so that
this is a quote from that woman who you
who you saw the drawing of right
who would put the rock down in front she
says my body by the way is always the
rover
this is a hard-nosed scientist or nasa
my body by the way
is always the rover so right here touch
his chest is the front of the rover
my magnets are right here touches the
base of her neck and my shoulders
are the front of the solar panel and
that means she moves forward and splays
her arms up
to other sides the rest of it so i have
all kinds of things and 10 is sticking
up over here adjusting to her back
laughs
but when i'm taking a picture of
something in the atmosphere then it
helps me to kind of look up
looks sits up and looks straighter being
the rover
and this is the front of me touches the
chest and then i put my head up
puts head up and looks back and forth uh
whatever to whichever vector i'm looking
at
so you see what like she's she's
completely identifying with the rover
in an embodied enacted way
so another scientist had this to say
because i want to talk about
what this sense of identification does
some other phenomenological markers
so another scientist said i was working
in the garden one day and all of a
sudden
i don't know what's going on with my
right wrist i cannot move it
out of nowhere i get here to the
planning meeting
and spirit that's one of the rovers has
its right front wheel stuck
things like that you know i am totally
connected
to spirit no pun intended there but
maybe a little bit
right like you see what's going on here
the phenomenology
borders on being magical such that the
identification is such
that right these weird synchronicities
become super salient to the scientists
another scientist said something similar
to say interestingly i screwed up my
shoulder and needed surgery
right about the time that opera
opportunities idd
arm started having problems with a stiff
shoulder joint
and i broke my toe right before spirit's
wheel broke so i'm just saying
maybe it's kind of sympathetic i don't
know
i mean i don't think there's any magic
involved or anything but maybe it's some
kind of unconscious
subconscious thing i don't know
try to show you how deep this
participatory knowing is
it's deep it's very profound it's
phenomenologically
very very present to the scientists
so notice we've got two things going on
here we've got
a coordinated manipulation of
perspectival knowing through the drawing
as
and a manipulation of participatory
knowing
through this this anthropomorphic
technomorphic looping and then when you
do that
you get the sense of presence you get
the sense
of being on mars you get a sense of
being
the rover on mars and that
sense is functional because it allows
you
to do the best field work through the
rovers
on mars
of course all of this is being done
implicitly and tacitly they don't
none of the scientists they discovered
this for themselves no but they didn't
go to
wow how to improve field work on mars
you know do this or do
they they have they have like
sort of right implicitly and tacitly
figured this all out in a collective
fashion
yes yes they've drawn on their intuitive
tendency for participatory knowledge to
embody this
exactly exactly
so
let's zero in on that connection now
between
the situational awareness that is given
to me by a sense of presence
so what is what am i proposing i'm
proposing that participatory knowing
generates affordances and then
perspective on knowing
turns those affordances into salient
affordances and salient affordances
within salience landscaping
is what we mean by situational awareness
situational awareness is the state you
need to have
in order to acquire and apply skills
situational awareness is the state you
need to have in order to acquire and
apply
skills so the procedural ability knowing
how to do something
is dependent on the perspective of like
knowing what it's like to be
which is of course also dependent and
interrelated with
you know knowing how to knowing no not
sorry
knowing by being the rover that's normal
right here
okay so now i want to i want to zero in
on
an important feature of skills so this
will seem like a digression for a bit
okay so we've got we've got this
argument built up here over here about
uh perspectival knowing participatory
knowing situational awareness
uh generating affordances making them
salient
uh et cetera that's all here so that's
trying to hold that
right now i want to the bridge of course
is to
acquiring and applying skills but i want
to note something very important about
skills now this goes to the work of
the neuroscientist reed montague he
sounds like a shakespearean figure right
who do we need now we need montague
right
and so he wrote a really uh he wrote a
really interesting book a while ago not
that long ago i think it was like
2010 i'm not i'm not sure i have to
check
i had a really provocative title it said
your brain is almost perfect
which is a really interesting um title
for a book
you're going to of course you're going
to pick that book up right
so anyways uh he makes the he
he first of all poses a problem um
uh and it's direct it's at the core of
skills
okay so if i'm going to engage in
skillful behavior
uh i want of course i want to be as
efficient as i possibly can
right because if i if you and i are in a
darwinian
competition and i can use some skill
more efficiently than you
i'm going to out-compete you right here
okay
so let's say that's relatively
non-controversial
okay so how do i make my skills more
efficient well one of the things you do
and you of course think about how much
you have to coordinate
in order to right you just
have to coordinate different things
together or let's say you
let's even use an analogy you're trying
to get a bunch of people to
work together well they have you have to
coordinate their behavior
well how do you coordinate their
behavior well they have to communicate
with each other
right and then right and there has to be
communication between the parts of my
hand
etc via the brain etc so the idea is
okay i increase the efficiency of this
skill
by increasing the internal communication
because that reduces
me working at cross purposes okay
working in internal conflict
etc so i can increase coordination
right and that's my increased
communication okay
but montague says but wait there's a
problem
the problem with that is right what
efficiency does
efficiencies not only improve the
product efficiency is also reduce the
cost
right right and he says the problem with
right
as you increase communication right is
the cost
of your processing goes up and it goes
up in a non-linear fashion
and that's why that's where you can get
the effect of all the people in the room
talking
there's so much cacophony and noise
right and trying to get that
right so the metabolic cost goes up
very rapidly so the brain seems like he
says it looks like the brain's caught in
a dilemma
it needs to increase if it needs to
increase efficiency
by increasing communication and it needs
to increase efficiency
by reducing communication by reducing
communications
oh
okay so there's all these important
trade-off relationships
okay so montague says proposes that the
brain
actually has a really powerful way of
solving
this problem
now in order to explain it he i'm going
to use his analogy um okay
and the analogy is of a a a a
a like an old married couple that
they're happily married
uh some people stay married so that they
can torture each other i
understand that so we're not talking
about that we're talking about people
that
have been together a long time and they
want to be together
and they have that almost telepathy they
seem to be able to communicate a lot
with very little
um i had a beloved aunt and uncle that
had exactly
that kind of relationship i think
everybody knows sure i'm talking about
it's like
well they don't actually have telepathy
um so montgomery says well what hack
what what do they have
is let's say i'll just uh
uh i'll just use his model it tends to
be uh
it's a model based on a straight
marriage but that's not relevant but
i'm going to use it because it's easier
for me to do the reference sure right
i can just talk about the man and the
woman it just makes it faster and easier
nothing else is implied by my by using
those terms about marriage or anything
like that okay
so the woman has internalized a model
of the man and the man has internalized
a model of the woman
there's what's called mutual modeling
they they mutually model
each other so that the woman can
actually have her behavior coordinated
with the man
without them having to talk to each
other because she just consults her
model
and he just consults his model so you
have
the right you have you see you what you
seem to be getting with this
is the benefits of increased
communication without actually
communicating
and thereby keeping the cost of
communication down
and so montague sort of leaves it at
that
right and i want to i want to do a
couple things to try and enforce
he just makes the claim that there's all
kinds of evidence that the brain is
doing this
and at a neuroscientific level you know
i'm sure he's right i'm not going to
challenge it but i want to i want to
bring up
sort of evidence that has a more
phenomenological feel to it
okay of this okay
so one is uh synesthesia
so synesthesia is the fact that
um you you get human beings in which the
you the information from one sense
modality seems to pass to the other like
people say i can taste
shapes right things that's a that's a
classic example
and what that means is that you've got
you've got sort of the tactile layer of
the brain
or at least one plausible explanation
and the
right and the taste area of the brain
are
right actually deeply mutually modeling
each other
you get you can get actually acquired
synthesis your two famous examples and
think of how this is gonna
right okay so you have bat boy and think
about thomas nagel is what it's like to
be a bat
okay so the batboy well there's there's
now i think 128 cases of this so it's
not some weird
loopy single case right he was he was
blind
and he tried himself like a bat he
taught himself echo location
he taught himself to make noises and use
the sound
and he reports having something like
visual experience but also not like
visual experience and it's he says it's
sort of out here
about this big so
he is using sound to do something like
seeing we also know
and this is reported by walsh and others
and something i can
said to as well long-term meditators
tend to get acquired synesthesia
they tend to start to get synesthetic
drift between the various sense
modalities
why because they're spending a lot of
time
right basically trying to get they're
spending a lot of time
doing this mutual modeling i'm gonna
that that's what you're doing when
you're sort of inside your
that inner space so you say well so what
well i want to point out to you
very quickly how synesthetic everybody
is so what i'm going to do
is i'm going to i'm going to show a
picture
okay and what i want everybody to do is
as rapidly as possible i'm going to show
a picture
i want you to point to the picture that
is uber and the picture that's
kiki okay
go so
overwhelmingly like 90 beyond 95 percent
concordance
people po to the right picture as bubba
even though i said booba first
and the left picture is kiki and
and and you go and you go well so what
that's
synesthesia what the heck is the
connection between
bubba and that picture and people will
say things
well bubba is kind of round and so is
the picture and you go
what do you mean bubba's round although
saying kiki is sharp
and that's sharp and you go what what
are you talking about
okay so all of this is evidence that
various parts of the brain
are mutually modeling each other the
visual cortex
and the auditory cortex right are
mutually modeling each other all the
time and that makes sense
right in terms of the coordination you
would need
for skill performance is that okay so
far
yes notice notice how
much this mutual model like think about
the bat point seeing how the mutual
modeling is actually affording
spectralization and all kinds of
interesting things
okay
so uh some of the work i'm doing with
anderson todd and richard wu and fa
unguen
on this model of consciousness right
we we try to we revise montague's idea a
little bit
because you know if my aunt and my uncle
never spoke again their models would
eventually drift apart
right right sure models would eventually
drift apart so periodically they do have
to come together
talk to each other and do any
corrections to distortions that are
coming
to the model right right i guess you get
that at times in couples therapy
where people have to come in and really
get back in tune with each other yeah
now you can actually see human beings
um shifting between these two modes you
can
right so let's take it that
i have my my like
my modules right and when i'm task
focused
they're just working they're focused on
the world and
my right and they're and one area of my
brain is relying on its model
of another area and vice versa so that
they can be highly coordinated together
okay but then there must be a period
where they have to stop doing that and
go back
and talk to each other and make sure
that they are properly
modeling each other so that the
integration isn't infected with
distortion
well what would that look like well that
would look like what happens to human
beings
they cycle between being task focused
and mind wandering
right in fact right you're so you're
focused and then your mind goes off
and in that it's and we know you know
you know
you get the default mode network is
highly engaged
and what's it doing there it's very
self-referential it deals with
information that's self
relevant and what do we know from the
work of celie and humphreys that
self-relevant information is the glue
it's how you glue things together
what does that mean practically it means
that i make sure that my models
are properly tracking each other so that
they can properly coordinate behavior
so you actually cycle in this way all
the time that's indicative
of something like this mutual modeling
centrally going on in your cognition at
many levels
now of course you can't just have mutual
model of everything because that would
be commentary explosive
come back to that issue later so
what i want to propose to you is that
skills
require recursive mutual modeling so
like uh you know why recursive well
different parts of
my finger have to be mutually modeled
my my little finger and then there has
to be mutual modeling between my fingers
and then between my fingers and my palm
between my fingers and my palm and my
thumb
and between my hand and my wrist right
and my hand and my wrist and my elbow
etc that's what i mean by recursive
modeling
is that okay all right would that be
also sort of the nested hierarchy of
modeling like
totally totally very much and
yeah i i know what you you you can do
with that so i could
i'm sure you're gonna do interesting
stuff with it but so ultimately there
must be mutual
and so now what i want to do is say okay
so we've got the notion of mutual
modeling
central to skills we have the notion of
recursive
between layers of mutual modeling
centered skills
we know that skills their acquisition
and their application is ultimately
dependent on perspectival knowing
and that the perspectival knowing is
ultimately dependent on
the participatory knowing here's one i
want to suggest you
that that is a a method kind of
coordination that's needed
such that i want to propose to you that
there must be mutual modeling between
participatory
and perspectival participatory knowing
is generating affordances that are
potentially relevant to perspectival
knowing
and perspectival knowing is selecting
which affordances
to make salient within situational
awareness participatory knowing
and perspectival knowing have to be
mutually
modeling each other and they would go
through cycles
where right they're more independently
operating
and then cycles where they're more
talking to each other to coordinate
to coordinate their modeling of each
other
and i'm arguing that that would be a
requirement
for um for any acquisition and
application of any skill
okay
[Music]
so to put it in more of a slogan and so
don't forget everything i've said and
just remember the slogan
but for mnemonic purposes mutual
modeling in the coordination not only
within
but between kinds of knowing
this now gives me a hypothesis or a
proposal
consciousness as the mutual modeling
between kinds of knowing
it's the mutual modeling between
participatory knowing
and perspective annoying okay the
participatory knowing of and through
perspectival knowing
and the perspectival knowing of and
through
participatory knowing so
what you've got here is right the
perspective of knowing is on the left
and the participatory is on the right
the perspective on knowing is giving me
aspectuality centrality temporality
it's giving me the adverbial qualia it's
giving me that demonstrative
indexicality the you know the this pure
nounist togetherness of consciousness
the participatory knowing is giving me
affordance generation
the co-shaping and fitting of the agent
of arena
and it's creating that inactive
co-variation between me and the
environment
you see what i'm doing i'm bringing back
the pieces of descartes
the participatory knowing is creating
these really uh
uh really affording co-variations
and then the perspectival knowing is
turning those co-variations
into something that is ready for skill
acquisition
analogous to how descartes proposed
right
that consciousness turned the
co-variations
into representations available for
reason
what i'm proposing is but the
perspective of knowing
with it right takes the co-variations
the affordances
from participatory knowing and
converts them into not what is ready for
reason
but what is ready for action what is
ready for skill acquisition
and skill application
all right that's the argument
that's the argument i wanted to make and
so
what i mean there's a lot of work we
still need to do we need we still need
to go in and take this way of thinking
right and all the all the machinery
we've worked and put it into
um deep discussion with
um some of the best models we have of
the functional nature of consciousness
but what they are
what i'm going to argue throughout is
that um
there's a deep convergence about what
the function of consciousness is
it's this higher order recursive
relevance realization
that allows us to ask specialized things
so that we can engage
in agent arena fitted action for the
world that's right
that's a lot of what the consensus is
about what consciousness
uh how it functions and what i've tried
to show you is
if you accept that functionality it
gives you so
much of the phenomenology it gives you
adverbial qualia it gives you the sense
of fittedness
it gives you the sense of what it's like
to be here now it gives you the
participatory knowing of consciousness
you
know you're conscious by being conscious
etc
right right um
so let me see if i can piece this
together a little bit in terms of the
uh just the frame of the perspectival
into the participatory and the dynamic
interrelationship between the two greg
i'm going to stop
sharing now so that we can have a more
direct thing
uh so let me let me share with you sort
of
a less developed model but one that i
found very
useful in the clinic room right uh
to see if this tracks some with some of
the
sort of what i would call intuitive
meaning non-self-conscious
but therefore i think you know
participatory
uh dynamic relations that people would
have
in their sequences of engagement
okay um and so when i i developed the
thing called the p
m e relation okay where p stands for
perception
right and that's going to head into
perspectival knowing
all right m stands for motivation
okay which has two different states of
approach
and avoidance okay and then e stands for
emotion which is to energize motive in a
particular
enter you know so so we see a lot of
uh for example is individuals perceiving
a particular event
referencing it in relationship to their
goals okay
getting emotion and then responding
accordingly as they try to
regulate the costs and benefits or
stressors and affordances
in a dynamic iterative pattern right
right
right so when i hear your participatory
knowing and think about the grip
of the agent arena relation and i think
about the components of that as to how
the system
is perceiving where it is thinking about
where it's trying to go
enacting particular affordances to
extract uh
those patterns of investments i see i
hear
a lot of similarity in that dynamic
relation so let me let me let me
ask questions to make sure i'm i'm
seeing
the same connection as you are so i i
expect that when you are working with
people
in a therapeutic context when you say
perception
you don't mean like just literal
perception you mean some you mean
something like how they've aspectualized
what aspect of the thing how they're
determining how it's salient and
relevant to them
right and then of course that is so
that's a perspectival knowing so i agree
with you there are we are we in sync
we're in safe there and then of course
but that's right
that is grounded in ultimately the sense
of identity that they're assuming
in connection with them how they're like
the agent arena participate
the participation and the affordances
that are available
but also the influences that become
unavailable in particular
so there could be ways i'm thinking also
of your sort of filters
there could be ways in which people
greg i'm not as well versus you so i'm
going to probably use this in the wrong
way so
be charitable with me but there's ways
in which people could repress
they could repress at a participatory
level because they could
refuse to bend on an identity and
therefore not have access to affordances
they could also repress at a
perspectival level
because they could be fixated on one
aspect
and not be able to pick up alternative
aspects is that is that 100
yeah absolutely absolutely so we can put
this let's put this in on and sort of uh
um so here let's see if this flies okay
in terms of the kind of both the models
that people have
so they're perspectival then will dot
dump into their
both identity and memory structures okay
so let's pull on
that kind of narrative um there's also
if we get into the person level
self-conscious justification
okay um but this may maybe just because
this resonates with me as a high school
kid
um i always liked this example my uh
when i was
so he was like he helped me see this
dynamic relation
as follows so let's say you're in a uh
you know a place and you see an
attractive person
over right right right and so now all of
a sudden you see the person
all right and then that you'll have a
perceptual gestalt
okay then if it's an attractive person
all right and your
and your motivational approach state
okay
is to enact that then you want to reduce
the discrepancy between where you are
and say in this case as a heterosexual
guy where she is
right right okay um so
i might then activate my
past scripts okay say procedural
participatory scripts
of the ways in which that dance might go
okay
one of the things then that uh i guess
what i'm suggesting
is that i'd like to think a little bit
more about how motivation
and emotion play in this participatory
chance
yes very much thank you very much so
i'll finish this little narrative
because it was
cute for me in that um so our according
to him and i think there is good
research for this although
it is complicated our approach
motivations operate on a slightly
different time
frame than our avoidance motivation okay
so what he said he what he said he did
and i had had a reflection on this as
well
is that far away from the room when you
see the attractive
woman your approach motivation sees the
possibility of success
and the stressors of getting rejected
are lesser
but as you move closer and closer the
time paths cross
so the threat of getting rejected then
meets you halfway across the room
which is why you get halfway over there
stop and turn back and head back to your
bar stool without asking her
or out and i had an ability to empathize
with that particular sequence
right um and so what what i'm saying
is that um uh the
to me that as we lay down this
participatory dance
the dynamic relations inter-psychically
between our perceptions our motivations
and our emotions
with the affordances and costs are
engaged in that that's how i talk about
sort of a behavioral investment flow
so great so let's pick up on two sides
of this
i'm going to quote read montague again
what's the difference between us and
computers
right uh well we don't care about the
information we're processing
we care about it and that's right that
there's
that's the fundamental right affective
commitment of limited times and
resources that's at the core of
relevance realization
and why do we care about information
processing
because we are auto poetic we are we
have to take
care of ourselves because we're always
making ourselves
so i think so if we remember that this
i'm proposing that this machinery is
ultimately all running on the relevance
realization machine right
secondly notice how you had different
components
and how right so
you can even see that cycle i was
talking about right
there they're sort of operating
independently right the approach
module and the avoid module and they're
probably they have they've got sort of
mutual modeling going on
and then it flips but in between there's
probably a moment where they're checking
in with each other
right right that moment of indecision
right right well right
right and so you can see the mutual
modeling function and so
you can see the mutual modeling function
and you can see the salience landscaping
interacting in directly in the example
you just gave directly in the example
you just gave and so
it's going to be inherently motivational
it's going to be and therefore it's also
going to be inherently aspectual it's
going to be centralized
it's going to be temporal it's going to
have temporality to it but there's going
to be all that what's it like to be here
you now
but it's also it's going to be relying
on
a mutual modeling between all that
perspectival knowing
and your sense of who and what you are
and what the arena is
the agent arena what are the affordances
here um
because you will of course it's not just
your perspective it's
the actual affordances that are
available to you so
you know if you're at a bar it's you're
much more likely to hit on a woman
than if you're at a funeral right and
things like that
just because the opportunities aren't
there for you right using the same way
so i i think again we can use this
this theoretical machinery you've been
developing to talk about all of these
examples and to cover off
a lot of the features that are
phenomenologically present
amen yeah yeah that's so that's
certainly what seems so exciting about
it
yeah so i think that you know what i'm
what i'm trying to add
to what what do i want to call the
literature on consciousness
with your help you know is these notions
of adverbial qualia
salience landscaping optimal gripping
respectable knowing situational
awareness
and participatory knowing and the mutual
modeling between perspectival and
participatory knowing
and that's a lot of new machinery that
we can use
and what's interesting about this
machinery is i'm proposing it
simultaneously allows us to talk
about the function of consciousness
right and the phenomenology
of consciousness and
and start to bridge between the function
problem and the generation problem
right well and for me where i come at
this you know because i
sort of as we talked about before i'm
very frustrated with psychology behavior
mental process
right right and then it's like actually
mental process has a there's a
neurocognitive functional view
of mental behavior and then there is
this perspectival
uh mind to consciousness deal and there
is this narrating
piece right but now what we can do at
least certainly what i feel
is i can now take mine too with all of
these new conceptual tools
right right and create such a much more
nuanced relationship to mind one
the interface between the various
domains right
and set up a nice cool little system and
then we'll talk more about how mine
three once all this stuff is ready for
reason
loops back and and creates an identity a
self-conscious identity or explicit
recursive function on top of all this
um but it really generates uh you know
like jonathan height you know talks
about the
um elephant and the writer right right
but this is like
well what is the machinery of that
elephant right right
what's really driving that elephant's
it's paths of affordance
and how does it dictate what it's
relevant realization processes and then
at what level of uh you know what are
the dynamics of that and that to me what
this
is is like oh there's so much richer
vocabulary
for all of that well that's what's
exciting uh for me
in the confluence between my work and
your work because
you keep making the case to me in a
convincing manner by the way
um that at least
this this this sorry this sorry turn it
the other way right
this work can at least contribute uh to
enhancing and enriching
the descriptive metaphysics that you see
that is missing and generating what you
call the problem in psychology
and i agree with you that these problems
the
the hard problem of consciousness and
that what maybe we could also call the
heart problem of psychology
right they they have to be addressed in
an integrated fashion
and if you feel right and you keep
making these connections to
uh to um to argue for it and so if you
if you are concluding more than just
feeling uh
that this argument also in a coordinated
fashion can help to advance
the overcoming of the heart problem of
psychology
then that's fantastic that's just
absolutely it's totally fantastic here
i'll give actually i just got this book
it's a good
it's a good book it's by uh bruce
goldstein it's called the mind
okay i read it you know it's but what it
is if you lead it through our lens i
would argue is
it's just basically mind one it's the
neurocognitive functional view of mind
one
it gives a chapter on the curiosities of
consciousness and then it ends with well
it's a hard problem and science doesn't
really look at it
and then the rest of the book is on the
hidden mind which is basically
the underlying information processing
and computation neurocognition
and then it's like okay it's all the
backstage machinery
but it basically and and it emphasizes
prediction and how it pulls out
particular relevance so it's
but so it's a brilliant neuro or i think
a well-done
up-to-date neurocognitive analysis okay
but if you were to read that it's like
well but then you have this whole part
of you that actually
sees the world yeah right and not to
mention a whole another part of you
actually talks about the world
people about the world that is
completely dependent upon because it's
intersubjective
so you get this picture of the mind um
and this is i think the same thing that
behaviorist did it's sort of like well
to get to the physica you know so
because they're embedded in a
physicality reductionist view
and because of the epistemology of
science it
it claps with one hand when we get into
interior pistol
interior epistemological consciousness
and it doesn't need to
um but that's essentially you know it's
like well we can't speculate on
unscientific things it's like
no we actually have introspective
awareness there's a lot of different
ways to angle this
and and the scientific you know exterior
epistemology is important in many ways
but that shouldn't
you know there are ways to integrate
what we can know from a first person
perspective
um so to me yeah this is so much of an
opportunity to
enrich in the picture and of course if
we think about the larger scheme of the
meaning crisis and how to help people
live their lives and what i do in
psychotherapy i mean it's like
obviously we're going to deal with
subjectivity in the real world oh yeah i
was going to say
that that book on the mind leaves you
with a picture of the mind that is
completely existentially irrelevant
it leaves out the first person
perspective and it leaves out
what you call mind three which is you
know your personhood
right and uh that k
i mean this sounds like whitehead but
you know that can't be an enough
that can't be an adequate account in
fact it seems to leave out
most of what we consider existentially
morally politically legally important
about
uh well i was going to say having a mind
but a better way of being a mind
being exactly and if we just knew okay
yes here's mind one
and you know and then like i i i talk a
little bit in my book
we talk about mind one a and mine one b
that's the
transition into behavior like and we
give good examples that like stephen
hawking so it's the
motor neuron disorder and boom you know
that system but
if we have the right vocabulary then we
can read that help people position it
and get all the good knowledge but not
think that's the whole picture that to
me is what's so
frustrating about our fragmented
psychology and yeah if we can help
uh bring psychology and cognitive
science together and say actually yeah
we have the edges of this problem
relatively well defined in a conciliate
coherent way
i think the utility of that is enormous
yeah i think so too and i think what you
said about
um you know this this is a view of
consciousness
that has the potential uh to help
ameliorate the meeting crisis
um i i yeah to me that's that for me
would be at the ultimate value
of what we're trying to do here
obviously to uh if that's the beauty of
your phraseology is like well
we need to realize what's relevant
[Laughter]
yeah right well that was the argument i
wanted to make today
and uh i i'm sorry it was a little bit
more monologic
but you were there it was helpful and um
like i said i don't intend to do this
again but there was things i wanted to
sort of show
this part needed to be sort of it was a
lot that needed to be laid out in a very
linear fashion
i think we've made the jump from
perspectival into participatory i think
the optimal grip is clear
i think you know this was a key element
and the whole rover thing is such a cool
story anyway
so yeah i enjoyed it hearing that uh
deeply and it was
you know it's impactful in terms of oh
yeah i do that with tetris
[Laughter]
so um i propose that we'll start turning
towards
some of the existing theories about uh
consciousness and
um and putting what we've built together
into a deep dialogue uh hopefully
mutually transformative
uh with those existing theories so if i
wanted to
uh as always thank you my friend this is
always
it's always fun it's always a lot of fun
and i really appreciate that
and so um i want to thank everybody
who's watching and
i look forward to meeting with you again
greg and i look forward
uh to uh interacting with uh with people
who are watching this series
amen great job we'll see you next time